Page 7, 7b, but we pick up on ו' עמוד ב' Vav
Amud Bet at the two dots. So we are discussing the משנה
Mishnah that is dealing with, that is dealing with special cases in
terms of ערך, Erech, and the specific issue was about somebody who's
terminal or somebody who's who has been decreed for execution. And now
we pick up with the two dots, רבי יוסי אומר נודר ומעריך.
Rabbi Yosei Omer Nodeh U'Ma'arich. So we shift from the question of
the object of ערך Erech to the question of can they obligate
themselves, they could be the subject, this person who's going to be
executed, to obligate themselves in a נדר, vow, an ערך, Erech, if
they damage they have to pay. And of course that was debated
in the משנה. Mishnah. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says the גמרא, Gemara, מי אמר דלא?
Mi Amar De'Lo? Whoever said they couldn't? אלא בנודר ומעריך ומקדיש כולי
עלמא לא פליגי. Ella Be'Nodeh U'Ma'arich U'Makdish Kulei Alma Lo Pligi. You're
right, they really are not debating the first three of those four
that were listed: vows, ערך, Erech, sanctifying. כי פליגי
באם הזיק.
Ki Pligi
Be'Im Hizik.
The real issue is
if a person that's about to be executed goes and damages somebody's
property, if he has to pay. Now the reason תוספות Tosafot says
that they know that that's the emphasis of the debate is that
his phrase was חייב, Chayav, at least our phrase is חייב, Chayav,
but some of the גרסאות Girsa'ot have חייב לשלם Chayav Leshalem or
חייב בתשלומין. Chayav Betashlumin. So the fact that you have to pay
compensation emphasizes that that was the focus of his statement. So that's
the issue, whether if you damage, the person who damages who's about
to be executed has to pay compensation. Now what's that
about? Let's take a look. תנא קמא סבר, Tanna Kamma Savar, the
official original תנא Tanna holds, אם
הזיק
אין
חייב בתשלומין,
Im Hizik
Ein Chayav
Betashlumin, you don't have
to. רבי יוסי סבר אם הזיק חייב בתשלומין, Rabbi Yosei Savar Im
Hizik Chayav Betashlumin, you have to. So okay, what's that about? במאי
קמיפלגי? Bemai Kamifligi? What are they debating? אמר רב יוסף במלוה על
פה וגובה מן היורשים קמיפלגי. Amar Rav Yosef Bemilveh Al Peh Vegoveh
Min Hayorshim Kamifligi.
If you have an oral loan, whether you can collect from the
heirs. Meaning, the general principle is is that a if a loan
is in a שטר, Shtar, in a document, then because that is
now a matter of public record, also perhaps because the document also
serves as an instrument to create the liens, then you have liens
on the property and then you can collect from people that purchased
the land or if the person dies, from his or her heirs.
However, if it is only an oral loan, so it's not a
matter of public record and you don't have an instrument to create
the liens, then the extant reason that you cannot collect from purchasers.
But maybe you can, and maybe you can collect from the heirs
in particular because maybe they're like a continuation of the father. There's
no, of course, there's no שטר, Shtar, there's just no document. And
there is, no, it's not the same public record as being written.
Okay, if there's not a קול. Kol. Anyway, so therefore that's the
issue. So why is this discussion of a loan? Well, it's not
a loan, but it's a debt that does not have an accompanying
writ. You damage property, so that creates a debt, but there's no
writ, there's no שטר. Shtar. So therefore is that type of a
debt, will it will it create liens that will now pass on
to the heirs? That's the question. So we're really not asking whether
the person who damaged is obligated, but he's about to be killed.
We're asking whether his heirs have to pay. So let's take a
look. תנא קמא סבר מלוה על פה אינו גובה מן היורשים. Tanna
Kamma Savar Milveh Al Peh Eino Goveh Min Hayorshim.
The first תנא Tanna holds that if it's an oral loan, which
means not a loan again, any debt that does not have a
שטר Shtar accompanying it, does not have a lien, so you cannot
collect from the heirs. רבי יוסי סבר מלוה על פה גובה מן
היורשים. Rabbi Yosei Savar Milveh Al Peh Goveh Min Hayorshim.
Yes, although you might not be able to collect from purchasers, you
can collect from heirs, they're a continuation, and therefore you can collect.
That's one way of framing the debate.
And the fact that it's הקדש Hekdesh or בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
doesn't give it any additional status?
Well, actually I'm going to get back to the הקדש, Hekdesh, but
note the גמרא Gemara said they don't debate הקדש Hekdesh and נדר,
Neder, they're only debating מזיק, Mazik, only debating the scenario where the
guy's about to be executed damages. So we're going to talk in
a minute why the same issue isn't relevant for מזיק Mazik and
נדר, Neder, essentially it's what Dov would say. But we'll get back
in one second, let's just finish this thought. רבא אמר דכולי עלמא
מלוה על פה אינו גובה מן היורשים. Rava Amar Dekulei Alma Milveh
Al Peh Eino Goveh Min Hayorshim. רבא Rava says everybody would agree
that if it were just a debt without a writ, you could
not collect from heirs. והכא במלוה הכתובה בתורה קמיפלגי. Ve'hacha Bemilveh Haktuvah
BaTorah Kamifligi. Here the point is it's not just a debt, it's
that this obligation is explicit in the תורה. Torah. תורה Torah explicitly
says that if you damage, you have to pay. Okay, so therefore
somehow that gives it greater weight and entitles you to collect from
heirs. Now the גמרא Gemara never exactly fully spells that out, but
it might have something to do with the fact that, you know,
that there's an assumption that if the תורה Torah is so explicit
about your debt, then there are liens associated. It's true it's still
not a matter of public record, I mean the תורה Torah is
public record, but nobody knows you in particular did the damage. Okay,
but nevertheless that is assumed maybe to have with it the weight
to create to create to create liens.
Which really makes sense, because even if you say that in the
beginning it may tell us that damage, he'll have to pay, it's
almost like he meant to say that his heirs don't have to
do anything, not even pay a loan.
Okay, but you know, how about also paying paying a loan? I
mean, why isn't that also, how can you say that the heirs,
you know, he borrowed a thousand a million dollars and the heirs
get off scot-free? So, you know, so it's the same so it's
not just a question of fairness. Right,
let's let's just finish the thought out. Let's finish the thought.
Let me just read the next line. Okay, so תנא קמא סבר
מלוה הכתובה בתורה לאו כשטר דמי. Tanna Kamma Savar Milveh Haktuvah BaTorah
Lav KeShtar Dami. ```text The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds that it's
not like it's written in a שטר shtar and therefore it's a
normal debt without a without any normal debt without a writ and
with nothing more to it and you can't collect from the heirs,
but רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei סבר savar ככתוב בשטר דמי. k'katuv b'shtar
dami. Sorry, sister. Varda,
I'm in the middle of a שיעור. shiur. I'll call you back,
okay? Yeah, okay, bye. She's calling to wish me מזל טוב. mazel
tov. Okay,
so
anyway, okay, so anyway, so that's the debate about whether that gives
it greater weight. In principle, maybe everybody would agree a normal thing
that didn't have a writ you can't collect from the heirs, but
maybe here because it's in the תורה, Torah, it gives it greater
weight. Let's just sort of finish just sort of finish this up
and then I will take off questions. ואיכא דמתני
להא, V'ika d'matni l'ha, some say this debate was on the following
משנה, Mishnah, not on our משנה, Mishnah, but on the following one,
which which
actually it's not a משנה, Mishnah, excuse me, it's a תוספתא Tosefta
in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. היוצא להרג, Hayotzei l'hareg,
if somebody is going out to be executed, same scenario, except rather
than damaging property, it's inflicting personal injury on a person. וחבל באחרים,
V'chaval b'acherim,
if he damaged other people, חייב, chayav, he is liable to pay
damage, meaning physical injury, personal injury. ואחרים שחבלו בו, V'acherim shechavlu bo,
פטורים, pturim, if they damage him, they're exempt. We'll see why, but
I mean he's about to be killed anyway, but okay, we'll see
about that in a minute. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar אומר omer אף הוא af hu שחבל באחרים shechaval b'acherim פטור,
patur, even if he damages others, he's exempt, שלא ניתן לחזרת עמידה
בדין, shelo nitan l'chazarat amidah b'din,
because you cannot get him, you cannot bring him to stand in
a judgment. So therefore, okay, so so how are you going to
actually and we're going to see and we're going to discuss this
a little later today, you cannot postpone his judgment his execution for
the sake of wait, I have I want to take him to
court first before you execute him. There's an idea in הלכה halacha
about actually once, you know, there's a very very slow and deliberate
in deciding somebody is liable for the death penalty, but once they
do, as opposed to America where you could be waiting, you know,
20, 30 years, here, you know, in הלכה, halacha, it's almost it's
extremely fast. They feel having a death penalty hanging over somebody's head
without actually executing it is considered a
מנוול menuval afflict, right?
And therefore you have to go ahead and take care do that
right away. So therefore you cannot what?
It's also for the מלכות, malchut, היוצא להרג, hayotzei l'hareg, not just
הלכה, halacha, no? If like you're condemned by the secular authorities, היוצא
להרג. hayotzei l'hareg.
Yeah, but we're not talking but that's not the context. So let's
not now we're talking about only within Jewish law, whether it's the
same, we'll talk about that later. So מכל מקום, micheol makom, anyway,
so that's his position. Since you can't take him to court, he's
going to get off. So let's take a look at what the
גמרא Gemara says. מכלל דתנא קמא סבר ניתן לחזרת עמידה בדין? Michlal
d'Tanna Kamma savar nitan l'chazarat amidah b'din? Does this mean that the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said
that you can actually take him to court?
So אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef במילוה על פה גובה מן
היורשים קמיפלגי. b'milveh al peh goveh min hayorshim kamifligi. No, no, no,
everybody agrees you can't take him to court. So you can't hold
the court case when he's alive. Now the reason that's relevant is
if you could hold the court case when he was alive, then
it would transform it from just an oral debt, from a debt
without any evidence, to a written debt. If the court ruled against
him and wrote out in the record of the court, so-and-so is
obligated a thousand dollars for damage, then it doesn't have that status
of an oral debt, then it's actually a debt with a writ.
But because we can't take him to דין, din, it's going to
be left at the level of an oral debt. So everybody agrees
with that. So what does the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma hold? So
תנא
קמא סבר Tanna Kamma savar במילוה על פה גובה מן היורשים קמיפלגי.
b'milveh al peh goveh min hayorshim kamifligi. תנא קמא סבר Tanna Kamma
savar מלוה על פה גובה מן היורשים, milveh al peh goveh min
hayorshim, that yes, although it remains at the oral level, at the
non-written level, you can still collect from the heirs. ורבי שמעון בן
אלעזר סבר V'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar savar אינו גובה מן היורשים. eino
goveh min hayorshim. No,
you cannot collect from heirs. So that's the same debate, okay? And
one other poss- there's always a twist with it, another possibility. רבא
אמר Rava amar
דכולי עלמא מלוה על פה אינו גובה מן היורשים. d'kulei alma milveh
al peh eino goveh min hayorshim.
Everybody could agree in principle that you cannot collect from heirs if
it doesn't have a writ. והכא בכתוב ככתוב בשטר דמי קמיפלגי. V'hacha
b'katuv k'katuv b'shtar dami kamifligi.
The question is that
since the תורה Torah says you pay for personal injury, does that
give it the additional weight because of that to allow you to
collect from heirs even though there was no accompanying writ? תנא קמא
סבר Tanna Kamma savar ככתוב בשטר דמי, k'katuv b'shtar dami, ורבי שמעון
בן אלעזר סבר v'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar savar לאו ככתוב בשטר דמי.
lav k'katuv b'shtar dami. And therefore the question is not what whether
if it were just oral, the question is does the fact that
it's written in תורה Torah give it more teeth? Now let's address
some of the questions. First I'll take the point that was made
first and then I'll go back to you, Michael, to your second
question. So the question is why are they only debating the case
of מזיק? mazik? How come it says the תוספות Tosafot would say
textually why are they focusing on מזיק? mazik? But logically shouldn't the
same issue be by נודר, noder, מעריך, ma'arich, and so on? If
I take if I if somebody takes a vow and then they're
executed, I mean somebody vows he has to pay he's going to
pay the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash a thousand dollars and then they're
executed, that's an oral debt and the same question should be whether
you can collect from the heirs or not. So the easiest case
where it's clearly not the same is הקדש. hekdesh. If he sanctifies
his cow, his car, his house, then it's not a debt, then
it's already owned by the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So of course
everybody would agree there that even if he's about to be killed
or whatever, the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash already owns the property. So
תוספות Tosafot says that we have to be assuming we're talking about
a similar scenario by נודר noder and מעריך, ma'arich, that the guy
said I vow
to
pay...``` If property was then designated for the fulfillment of that vow,
then it becomes sanctified and already owned for the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash and therefore it doesn't matter if he's executed afterwards. So it's
not so obvious that that's the scenario, but nevertheless תוספות Tosfos says
we have to be talking when we're excluding cases of נודר, Noider,
מעריך, Maarich, and מקדיש, Makdish, certainly מקדיש, Makdish, that they're excluded because
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash already owns it. But when it's just a
debt and it's not owned yet, then we have the issue about
whether you can collect from the heirs.
But if he set aside money for that debt?
Doesn't matter, it's not owned yet. הקדש Hekdesh has that magic, as
it were, that as soon as you set it aside, it becomes
sanctified. Okay, but if I set aside money to pay you, something
happens to that money, it's not like I've already paid you, right?
So my question before was, you know, we say that, you know,
that maybe חוב מיורשם Chov MeYarshem or not is a matter of
debate and whether he has a halachic right. I think we end
up saying that, you know, לפנים משורת הדין Lifnim MiShuras HaDin they
should do it anyway, right? The יורשים? Yorshim?
Well, that's an interesting question about somebody that can't collect, but you
know that you owe money, you have a חיוב בידי שמים. Chiyuv
Bidei Shamayim. Normally we say that about the person himself, he might
have a חיוב בידי שמים Chiyuv Bidei Shamayim under those cases. I'm
not so sure we say it by heirs because they never incurred
a personal obligation. It was their father's obligation, it wasn't their obligation.
So even for guys that damaged?
Right, it's a נעבעך nebach for that guy, but it wasn't they
who did it, it was their father who did it. So yeah,
I don't think we ever say, I could look, but I would
be very hard, I do not believe we ever say that that
sense, that comes from a personal obligation of having done the act.
But for them it's only a question of whether there's an actual
lien and that what they're personally obligated. They don't have a personal
responsibility for what their father did.
Just one final question. Yeah. Because I
was under the impression that יוצא להרג Yotzei LeHareig didn't say יוצא
להרג על ידי בית דין, Yotzei LeHareig Al Yedei Beis Din, just
יוצא להרג. Yotzei LeHareig. And you're saying is it's really all in
the context of a Jewish law court? But what if, and let's
say it is?
No, so you're right, there is an issue of עינוי דין. Inuy
Din. עינוי דין Inuy Din is limited to a case about Jewish
court. But if it's the issue of מלווה כתובה בתורה, Milveh Kesuvah
BaTorah, then really you don't even need this whole discussion about יוצא
להרג. Yotzei LeHareig. Really all you need to say is the guy
was מזיק mazik and he died, right? So the יוצא, Yotzei, so
it's a little funny that the way the גמרא Gemara frames the
debate. The debate seems to be, if you were just reading it,
the fact that a person is about to be executed, to what
degree is he still considered enough of a legal entity and a
person in law that he can incur obligations? That's really what you
would have thought the issue was, and it's specifically because he's about
to be executed and he already has the judgment passed against him.
The way the גמרא Gemara reframed it, it has nothing to do
with the fact that he's about to be executed, but to really
a simple question, somebody incurred a debt and he died. But this
is also גוסס, Goses, right? I mean, it's not just יוצא. Yotzei.
And the
גמרא Gemara has said
we're not talking, right. Well, right, now that we've talked about this
issue, it could be even by גוסס. Goses. But it could even
be by a
healthy person who drops dead the next minute. So that
is absolutely true. And by the way, though, so it is true
that the simple sense would have been whether such a person is
a enough of a legal person to incur obligation, but the גמרא
Gemara really says of course he is. The גמרא Gemara does not
want to even suggest that that's not true. But then the question
is, what is therefore the logic of the opinion that says that
if somebody damages him, that you don't have to pay damages, right?
That seems to indicate that we no longer recognize him as a
legal entity because there was the opinion that if he himself is
personally damaged, there's no obligation. So if you take a look and
here it is the emphasis that it is because he is going
to be executed in a Jewish court. The small רש"י Rashi on
the bottom of ו עמוד ב, Vov amud beis, רש"י Rashi says
פטורים peturim if he is personally injured, דאין לו דמים, de'ein lo
damim, ועומד הוא לחבל. ve'omed hu lachavel. So he has two explanations.
Number one is he has no value because he's about to be
killed. Now that's a bit of a question, you know, because when
a person, you pay damages for a person, it's not just their
market value. Meaning even if we, even if it's one aspect, how
much is your arm worth based on a market value, so who's
going to pay for somebody who's about to be killed? But there
are other damages, בושת, boshes, embarrassment, injury, you know, pain and suffering,
all of that. So then רש"י Rashi says the next line, which
is, I gotta turn this off, רש"י Rashi then says the next
line, which is, which is, that ועומד הוא לחבל. ve'omed hu lachavel.
He also הלכה halacha is it says that he has to now
be killed. So somebody who is in a position to be killed,
if you are as it were conceptually beginning the process by injuring
him, you can't really consider that to incur an obligation to that
person. Now you could still say not true, you know, we don't
say if somebody's about to die, if you kill them you haven't
committed murder. But okay, that's not their legally dictated and mandated. But
nevertheless, you could say you're not an agent of the court, who
gave you a right to go ahead and injure this person? But
anyway, here at least is where you see the idea that specifically
because he's going to be executed by a Jewish court, it changes
the legal status. But the גמרא Gemara resists that explanation in terms
of his being obligated to others. It only considers it... For him,
for you being obligated to him. For him being obligated to others,
the גמרא Gemara says he definitely is a legal entity, and the
only question is whether it can pass on to the heirs. Okay,
so let's now continue in the גמרא. Gemara. Yes. Two questions. One
is, is a debt part in the category of damages? Yes, debts
are in the category of damages. What do you mean debts are
in the category of damages? I hope that's the way it was
being discussed, it sounded like a debt was a damage. No, no,
no, if you actually physically damaged him, if you physically... No, not
that, earlier. No, no, no, it was that a damage is a
debt. If somebody damaged somebody physically or their property, that incurs a
debt. Okay, that's the way. And therefore the question is, once now
you have a debt, does that pass down to the heirs? Okay,
damage is a debt, not the other way. Yeah. And the other
question just from this last discussion, why couldn't the heirs be... why
couldn't the person who injures a person who's about to be executed
be responsible to pay the heirs? So that's exactly what I said.
There the גמרא Gemara actually says, and רש"י Rashi sort of distilled
it, that there it is about him not being a full legal
entity, or not being fully entitled to payment to his person because
his person is about to be sort of executed by the court.
Okay, but if let's say it was his property that you damaged,
you'd have to pay the heirs. But if you damaged his person,
you don't have to pay the heirs. So it's a little ironic,
but it has to do with the fact that he's about to
be executed. Okay, so let's now go, let's now continue. The גמרא
Gemara says like this. מיתיבי, Meisvei, I'll ask you on this because
basically we sort of put it out there that the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma of our משנה Mishnah holds that there is not an
obligation, and here we're going to have a סתם משנה Stam Mishnah
that says there is an obligation by the case of the heirs.
Let's take a look. החופר בור ברשות הרבים, Hachofer bor birshus harabbim,
somebody digs a hole, a well in רשות הרבים, rishus harabbim, he
has no right to do it, so he's liable for any injury
that happened, and not only injury to others, he's going to be
now the object of the injury, the sort of the victim of
the injury. ונפל עליו שור והרגו, Venafal alav shor vehargo, he's still
in the bottom of the pit digging his illegal well, and an
ox comes by and falls on him and kills him. Okay, so
פטור, patur, the owner of the ox does not have to pay
any damages, anyway you don't pay damages really for a person gets
killed, but we won't talk about that right now. Anyway, doesn't pay
any damages, the guy brought it on himself, he was the negligent
party. דלא, אלא שמת השור, אם מת השור, יורשי בעל הבור חייב
לשלם דמי שור לבעלים. Delo, ela shemeis hashor, im meis hashor, yorshei
ba'al habor chayav leshalem dmei shor laba'alim. So the heirs of the
guy who dug the well have to pay the owner of the
ox. Don't come to me that your father died, he dug the
well, it was his own fault, and by the way, you now
have to pay me for my ox because your father made a
well that killed my ox. Okay, and that's what... so it's a
very graphic case. אמר רב אילא אמר רב, Amar Rav Ila, Amar
Rav, so anyway, so here we've got a problem because here you
see the debt passes down to the heirs. And now, of course,
why is it such a problem? We said there are opinions that
say that if it's even if it's על פה al peh it
passes to the heirs, or if it's כתובה בתורה ksuva batorah it's
like it's כתובה בשטר. ksuva beshtar. But nevertheless, the question is that
it doesn't fit with the סתם stam of our משנה, Mishnah, which
says that it does not pass down to the heirs, the way
the גמרא Gemara is reading it. So how do you reconcile it?
So אמר רב אילא אמר רב, Amar Rav Ila, Amar Rav, כשעמד
בדין. keshe'amad b'din. We're talking about that there was already a court
case. And as I said before, once there's a court case, it's
no longer like an oral debt. Once there's a court case, it
becomes an official record of the court and it becomes like a
written debt. And therefore, of course, it passes down to the heirs.
So the גמרא Gemara says, והרגו קתני, vehargo ktani, but it says
the ox fell on him and killed him! Who had time to
have a court case? It killed him as it fell on him!
אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, כשעשאו טריפה.
keshe'asa treifa. It didn't really kill him. It just made him... it
was a fatal wound, and they had enough time to schlep him
to court and have a court case before he eventually died. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says, והאמר רב נחמן, veha'amar Rav Nachman,
but didn't רב נחמן Rav Nachman say, תני חגא, tani Chaga, that
חגא Chaga said, or something, תני תנא, tani tana, that the תנא
Tanna taught, who knows, some חכם, chacham, מית וקברו, meis u'kvaro, that
actually what happened was where it killed him and dirt fell in
on top of him and that became also his grave. So they
really... very colorful scenario. The ox fell and with the ox... okay,
so anyway, no, it's not possible to say there was a court
case here. So you see it passes down to the heirs again.
There are those positions, but how do you explain this ברייתא braisa
if that is not your position? So the גמרא Gemara says, והלכתא,
vehilchasa, so the הלכה halacha is, which is a funny phrase, but
it means here's the only way to explain this according to that
approach, דיתבי דייני אפומא דבירא. deyavti dayani apuma deveira. The judges were
sitting right there at the edge of the well! So they saw
the whole thing, and this probably draws on principles in סנהדרין Sanhedrin
that if judges see it, you don't need to accept testimony, their
direct observation is like they can testify. So therefore, of course, you
still wonder at what stage does it become a debt? They still
probably have to get out the words, פלוני אתה חייב. Ploni atah
chayav. So somehow they get out those words before he actually dies
and the dirt falls in. I don't know. Anyway, it's clearly without
that, it clearly It clearly seems to be go clearly is going
according to the approach that says that it does pass down to
the heirs. Yes. Would he would he be able to say if
an עוף off falls? No. No, that's because you have to actually
have a court case that your case to transform the nature of
the debt. And you don't actually have to go and pay anything?
You have to give a התראה. hatra'ah. No, no, no, it's just
all civil. It's not about it's not about מלקות malkus or מיתה,
misa, it's all about civil cases. What if the person says? Okay,
so right, so those are different, but here it's just a question
about civil liability, then you have to... Anyway, now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. All right, היוצא להרג, Hayotze
lehareg, somebody who is going out to be executed. Halachically. Now, halachically,
and here the issue is now shifting to the concern about whether
about not postponing the judgment. That actually was carried on to the
next משנה, Mishnah, we'll see. מזין עליו מדם חטאתו ומדם אשמו. Mazin
alav midam chatato umidam ashamo. If this guy had to bring a
חטאת chatas or an אשם asham for some other sin that he
did בשוגג, beshogeg, now of course if he dies, then it's going
to be a חטאת chatas or an אשם asham that the owner's
died, and then you're not going to be able to bring it
to the קרבן. Korban. The חטאת chatas will have to die, the
אשם asham will have to wait to get a מום. mum. So,
can you now bring the קרבן Korban quick, quick, quick, bring the
קרבן Korban before he gets executed so that we don't have to
be stuck with a חטאת שמתו בעליה? chatas shemetu ba'aleha? So yes,
you can. Even though he's going out to be executed, bring the
קרבן Korban for him. Don't say, for example, if he's going to
be executed, he what, you know, who the כפרה kapparah isn't going
to do him any good, or don't say he's no longer a
legal entity. We already said he's a legal entity. So yes, bring
his קרבן Korban for him. It will do him some good? What?
It will do him some good, and that's why we are bringing
the קרבן, Korban, and he is a legal entity. Okay. חטא באותה
שעה, Chata be'otah sha'ah, now as he's walking, as he's walking to
the place of execution, he sees some nice meat and he picks
it up and eats and it actually happens to be חלב chelev
and therefore he now has done another איסור כרת. issur kares. Now
can he bring a קרבן Korban for this sin that he did
as he's about to be executed? חטא באותה שעה אין נזקקין לו.
Chata be'otah sha'ah ein nizkakin lo. Then we don't bother. We don't
bother with it. We're not going to bother bringing the קרבן. Korban.
מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why not? Since we're assuming he is a
legal entity and the כפרה kapparah can do him some good. So
אמר רב יוסף מפני שאין מענין את דינו. Amar Rav Yosef mipnei
she'ein me'anin es dino. We don't want to postpone his judgment. And
therefore it's going to take time to get the קרבן, Korban, bring
it to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר ליה אביי אי הכי, Amar lei Abaye i hachi, if that's
a concern and we won't postpone it even to get his כפרה,
kapparah, then אפילו רישא נמי. afilu reisha nami. So even in the
beginning that he already had sinned from a week ago, why do
we wait to bring his קרבן? Korban? It's going to take time.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no. רישא, Reisha, no, that case כגון
שהיה זבחו זבוח באותה שעה. kegon shehayah zivcho zavuach be'otah sha'ah. That
case isn't we had to get the קרבן Korban and bring it
to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. There they had already שחט shechted
the קרבן Korban and they got report that this guy was about
to be executed and the כהנים Kohanim say, what can we do?
Can we sprinkle the blood? And the answer is yes. So there
was no postponement, it was all taking place already. So that's why
it was allowed. But any postponement we would not do. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אבל אין זבחו זבוח מאי? aval ein zivcho zavuach
mai? So what would you say if the sacrifice had not already
been slaughtered? לא, Lo, then you would say you don't wait to
bring it. So אדתני, ad'tani, so why do we go to the
case חטא באותה שעה אין נזקקין לו, chata be'otah sha'ah ein nizkakin
lo, that only if he sins at that moment you not bring
a קרבן? Korban? לפלוג ולתני בדידיה. Liflog uletani bedideih. Why not distinguish
even within a case where he's already sinned in the past? במה
דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, when do you bring the קרבן Korban
for him if he sinned in the past? שהיה זבחו זבוח באותה
שעה, Shehayah zivcho zavuach be'otah sha'ah, if the קרבן Korban already slaughtered.
אבל אין זבחו זבוח לא, Aval ein zivcho zavuach lo, if it
hasn't already been slaughtered, even though it was a sin of the
past, you do not wait the time that it will take to
bring it. So the גמרא Gemara says, הכי נמי קאמר, Hachi nami
ka'amar, that's really what we mean to say. במה דברים אמורים, Bameh
devarim amurim, when can we bring the קרבן? Korban? שהיה זבחו זבוח
באותה שעה, Shehayah zivcho zavuach be'otah sha'ah, if it was already slaughtered.
אבל אין זבחו זבוח, Aval ein zivcho zavuach, but if it hadn't
already been slaughtered, then נעשה כמי שחטא באותה שעה, na'aseh kemi shechata
be'otah sha'ah, it's just as it's equivalent to if he had just
sinned
now, ואין נזקקין לו, ve'ein nizkakin lo, and you do not bring
it. So it's like, yeah, you're right, we sort of jump to
a more extreme case, but we really mean is anything that would
lead to any postponement, it's like the case of sinned now, we're
not going to postpone it for his כפרה. kapparah. So again, the
גמרא Gemara reads that the concern here is postponing his sin, but
again, a simple read of this משנה Mishnah and ברייתא Braisa would
have been similar to the issues right before about questions about is
he liable and so on, which is a question of to what
degree is he a legal entity. And to what degree do we
care about things that he does? So if we don't care, let's
say he doesn't have to pay if he damages, he doesn't have
to pay whatever, maybe if he does a sin, it doesn't have
the same significance.
If he does a sin now as opposed to having done a
sin before. So the simple sense of these משניות Mishnayos and ברייתות
Braisos are questioning how much his actions are meaningful now that he's
about to be executed. But the גמרא Gemara basically rejects that. It
assumes he's completely a legal entity, the actions are totally meaningful, and
the only question is whether the debt passes on to the heirs,
whether under certain circumstances whether it will lead to a postponement of
the judgment, and that's
how the גמרא Gemara framed the issues. Okay. Now we take a
look at the next משנה, Mishnah, which, if you thought that when
we had discussions before about, I don't know, מגילה Megillah reading and
זימון, zimmun, you weren't expecting that in ערכין, Erchin, here's going to
be something you're certainly not expecting in ערכין, Erchin, one or two
lines in the גמרא Gemara that are very critical for a major...
no. temporary debate. So let's take a look. Sorry, we'll talk about
it later.
האישה שיצאה ליהרג,
Haisha sheyatza l'hareg, a woman now is about to be executed. We're
talking about executing a man, although we got onto this topic because
of questions of ערכין, Arachin, now we're on the topic about people
that are about to be executed. So a woman who's about to
be executed, אין ממתינין לה עד שתלד, ein mamtinin lah ad sheteled,
you do not wait if she's pregnant for her to give birth.
You will execute her even when she's pregnant. האישה שישבה על המשבר,
Haisha sheyashva al hamashber, once she's on the birth stool, then ממתינין
לה עד שתלד,
mamtinin lah ad sheteled, then you do, then you do wait.
Although presumably the principle why you don't wait is עינוי הדין, inuy
hadin, which we already said, that is overridden when she has already
begun the birth process. Why? You could have just said at that
stage it would be completely, you know, inappropriate, like a ביזיון, bizayon,
to take a woman in the middle of birthing and execute her
at that moment. רש"י Rashi says though differently. רש"י Rashi says no,
if she's at the
moment of giving birth, then the
child has, because part of the reason we're allowed to execute, and
this is why you could have already guessed this is very
relevant to the question of abortion, is that earlier we consider the
child basically to be one entity with her. Once she's starting to
give birth, it's considered to be a distinct entity. The question though
that's raised is normally the fetus is only considered to be born
when the head emerges, not when she is starting to give birth.
So does this mean now that there's a middle stage, right? There's
when he's totally an entity with the mother, separate entity but not
yet a full person, right, which is how a lot of people
think about abortion, that it, you know, is a quasi-life, a legal
entity but not yet a full person, and then born as a
full person. So that is possible the way רש"י Rashi explains this.
I'm just saying that something completely different, that the pain of the
childbirth overrides any עינוי הדין. inuy hadin. In other words, you're kind
of distracted from your עינוי הדין. inuy hadin.
The pain of childbirth would kind of, right, negate the fact that
you're experiencing any עינוי הדין inuy hadin because you're focused on... that's
a good point too. Meaning... now, like you can't kill a woman...
right, well that's the point. I mean, that's the real point is
could you imagine that a court would execute her in the middle
of childbirth? And as the גמרא Gemara writes, that's really what seems
the simplest explanation. The גמרא Gemara talks about ביזיון bizayon and we'll
talk about that in a minute. Could you really imagine anything more
ביזיון bizayon than killing a woman in the middle of childbirth? But
your explanation is also possible. Anyway, there are... so I hear what
you're saying, that she's focused on that and there's no sense of
עינוי הדין. inuy hadin. I understand. What I'm saying also did not
have to do with the status of the fetus. So there are
definitely ways of explaining this that does not say something about the
status of the fetus before its birth. But nevertheless, רש"י Rashi interprets
it to be about the... no, no, no, the first part, the
first part. Yes, yes, yes, I didn't mean that. The second part
about in the process of childbirth you don't do it, רש"י Rashi
explains that that says that the fetus at that stage gains independent
identity. But that is not how you have to... all we're saying
about that aspect in the middle of childbirth, there's other ways of
explaining it. You could explain what Dov said, that there's no עינוי
הדין. inuy hadin. You could explain what I said, you can't execute
a woman under those circumstances. But רש"י Rashi explains it that the
fetus gains independent identity. Now, האישה שנהרגה, Haisha sheneherga, totally different point.
If the woman was executed, נהנין בשערה, nehenin bise'arah, there is no
prohibition of deriving benefit from the hair. You're not allowed to derive
benefit from a corpse. We have whole questions about autopsies and not
autopsy, dissections for people that are becoming doctors. And the basic answer
there is other, is that sort of like educational benefit is not
real הנאה, hana'ah, I mean not הלכתית הנאה, halachitit hana'ah, real הנאה,
hana'ah, but anyway. But you're not allowed to derive benefit from a
corpse. Also a question about transplants, from cornea transplants from people that
are already clearly already dead. Is that benefit or not? And how,
you know, maybe it is, it is, but it's overridden, maybe you
don't call it... anyway. So you can't derive benefit from a corpse,
but the משנה Mishna says you can actually shave her hair and
use her hair for like a wig. You can derive benefit from
her hair. So you think the hair is not considered part of
the body, but we will discuss that in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
בהמה שנהרגה, Behema sheneherga, אסורה בהנאה. asura behana'ah. Now, if an animal
was executed, meaning it was like the שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, it
gored somebody and it was executed by בית דין, Beis Din, then
it is forbidden in benefit and you cannot derive הנאה, hana'ah, which
seems, you know, pretty obvious, but here we're just collecting issues about
people that are executed. What? Right, people that are executed, men, women,
and animals. But right, presumably also even their hair and their wool,
and we'll talk about that in the גמרא. Gemara. So let's take
a look now at the first part, which is of course, as
I said, extremely relevant for the abortion debate. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, פשיטא גופא היא. Pshita gufa hi. Now those three
words, oh my God, how much halachic import have been in those
three words? Because here's the point, right? There's a משנה Mishna that
says that if a woman is in childbirth and her life is
at risk, then before the child is born, you can, you can
basically dismember the fetus in utero in order to save her life.
And there's a גמרא Gemara that discusses in סנהדרין Sanhedrin that scenario
and describes the fetus maybe as something like a רודף, rodef, somebody
that's coming after the mother. life. So if you just focused on
that, you would say that's the exception. Generally you could never commit
abortion, right? It's like it's almost like a life, or it's a
quasi-life, but if the mother's life is at risk, that's a special
exception. Okay, whereas but but the general rule is that it's forbidden.
Then you get this גמרא. Gemara. This גמרא Gemara says you're allowed
to do it. So so now you have to say which is
the rule, which is the exception? So this is basically what the
debate over abortion boils down to in הלכה Halacha is which גמרא
Gemara you favor. Do you say this גמרא Gemara that you execute
the woman is the rule, meaning not that you execute the woman,
but it's the rule that it shows that we don't consider the
fetus to be part of the mother, okay, and that's really the
rule? And yes, the גמרא Gemara there talks about about the child
because the mother's life is at risk, but you know what? That
was an extreme case, but you don't even need that case. Basically
the fetus is part of the mother and it's really not a
problem to abort a fetus. Okay, because it's not a life. Right,
because it's not a life. Exactly. It's part of the mother but
it's not a life. Exactly, exactly. And this משנה Mishna tells you
the rule. That's one way of reading it. The other way of
reading it is no, no, no, this over there, that basically tells
you that the rule is that the only case is when the
mother's life is at risk. What do you do with this? Oh,
this is an exception. Here it's because since there's a הלכה Halacha
that you kill her and the child only dies incidentally, and therefore
it's specifically because of the mandate of execution and this is a
this is the exception. Now, the problem with that approach is the
first three words of the גמרא. Gemara. Because when the גמרא Gemara
says פשיטא גופא היא, Pshita gufa hi, it's not saying oh, of
course because there's a mandate of execution and therefore this is only
incidental etc. It just says of course, it's all one, it's all
her body, it's presumably it's not a life, it's not a separate
life. So those three words carry a lot of import in indicating,
you know, that whether we assume that abortion fundamentally, I mean nobody's
saying like it's מותר סתם, mutar stam, but anyway, how deeply problematic
it is. This גמרא Gemara seems to say that it is not
so deeply problematic. So what do you do with that? All right,
so I'm just framing the issue. They still say yeah, it doesn't
mean it, it's because of this context that you're executing her, I
don't know. Anyway, let's go on. איצטריך, Itztarich, you need it. סלקא
דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I would have thought... Wait, doesn't גופא
gufa mean it belongs to her? I don't think it's about ownership.
I think it's about it is seen like a limb of her
body, I think is more what it means, it's part of her.
But since it says that, then couldn't you not say then it's
a woman's option? Right, yeah, even... Yes, the simple meaning of this
גמרא. Gemara. Right, again, I wouldn't sort of call it ownership, but
it's a part of her body and she can treat it like
she would treat other parts of her body. Right, that is why
I said that the fact that the גמרא Gemara frames it as
פשיטא Pshita gives weight to say that this גמרא Gemara is more
of the rule and not more of the exception. So that is
part of the whole abortion discussion, absolutely. Now, for example, there are
some תוספות Tosafot that say, and תוספות Tosafot here, the שיטה מקובצת
Shita Mekubetzet actually says מותר. mutar. It doesn't just say like, you
know, it says מותר mutar to abort fetuses. Really? Okay, yeah, and
it's in תוספות Tosafot in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Anyway, רב משה פיינשטיין Rav
Moshe Feinstein who takes the exact opposite approach and says that aborting
fetuses is essentially murder, it's just you don't get executed in court,
he basically says, you know, they obviously did not mean it when
they said מותר, mutar, that was לאו דווקא lav davka etc. Anyway,
this is the abortion debate. Let's keep on going. All right, so
פשיטא, Pshita, yeah, of course. פשיטא גופא היא, Pshita gufa hi, of
course, it's her body. So it's of course and therefore she can,
you know, of course if you're going to kill her, you don't
have to worry about the about the fetus. איצטריך. Itztarich. No, it's
a חידוש. chiddush. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I would have
thought, הוה כתיב, hava ketiv, the verse says כאשר ישית עליו בעל
האשה, ka'asher yashit alav ba'al ha'isha, that if the woman if a
fetus actually is aborted by another person in a fight with another
man, right, and it accidentally leads to an aborting fetus, that he
has to pay a fine to the father. So ממונא דבעל הוא.
mamona de'ba'al hu. So here you actually get back to the concept
of ownership. Maybe therefore the father has a money interest in the
fetus or it's considered his property more literally. ולא ליפסדיה מיניה. v'lo
lifsadei minei. So maybe the father can say, listen, I understand you're
killing my wife or the mother of my unborn child, fine, whatever,
she deserves it, she did her trip, but that's my fetus and
therefore I have a right and therefore I demand that you don't,
you wait till it's born. So קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan,
so it tells you no, that we don't we're not interested in
the father's rights. ואימא הכי נמי, v'eima hachi nami, why not say
that? אמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי יוחנן אמר קרא, Amar Rabbi Abbahu
amar Rabbi Yochanan amar kra, ומתו גם שניהם, u'metu gam shneihem, לרבות
את הולד. l'rabot et ha'valad. They shall both die, this is in
a case of adultery. So that includes even the child. So we
think we're learning it from the word שניהם. shneihem. But of course
שניהם shneihem means the man and the woman. So the גמרא Gemara
says, wait a minute, והאי מיבעי ליה עד שיהיו שניהם שוים. v'hai
mibayei lei ad she'yihyu shneihem shavin. Doesn't it mean that they both
have to be equivalent? What this means is, I won't get into
it, there's a whole debate in the גמרא Gemara and תוספות, Tosafot,
but anyway, it might mean that only if both are adults in
the act of adultery, but if one's an adult and one's a
child, then since we don't kill one, we don't kill the other.
Although there are there's a משנה Mishna that actually says that you
would, but anyway, there are opinions that may and we need it
to tell me that they both have to be liable. So דברי
רבי יאשיה, divrei Rabbi Yoshiya, at least that's what... at least that's
what רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshi* says. So the מדרש *midrash*: כי קאמרת
מגם *Ki kamarta migam*, not getting it from שניהם *sheneihem*, I'm getting
it from גם *gam*. So you kill them and גם *gam* also.
Who else is there? Well, it's the unborn child. Let's say they
committed adultery and now there's an unborn child as a result, kill
them all. Okay, so therefore, now of course you could say there
in that case the father loses his money rights because he's also
being executed. But let's, I don't know, let's say he committed adultery
with not that the child was conceived in the adultery, he committed
adultery with a married pregnant woman. So you would kill the adulterer
and the adulteress and the and the fetus and the father's and
the father's property rights are ignored. So yes, that might have been
a claim, but we ignore it. So again, the very fact that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* frames it at most what its concern is,
the father's property rights, you know, again, really is a significant, very
significant in the questions about the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s approach to abortion.
You had a question? I was going to say if she's being
executed for adultery, maybe it's not the father's child in the first
place. Right, but let's say she's clearly pregnant, I don't know, you
could create a scenario, okay, every right. All right, so that is
a very powerful גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you know, sort of obviously heavily
contested and debated what exactly it means. Now we move on. ישבה
על המשבר yashva al hamashber, *Yashva al hamashber*, now she is sitting
in childbirth. So I said before that it was רש"י Rashi *Rashi*,
but now we're actually going to see where רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* gets
it from. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*? What's the reason? כיון דעקר גופא
אחרינא הוא *Keivan de'akar gufa achrina hu*. Once it is uprooted, meaning
once she's in the process of childbirth, then it actually is a
separate entity, which doesn't yet mean it's a full life, for that
it'd have to be born, but at least it's not one with
the mother and just because you're executing the mother doesn't mean you
execute the child once the child has some independent status. So although
in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* you could have said it meant it
was another reason, what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* said really is based on
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. You're saying אחרינא *achrina* means if you kill
it you're not חייב *chayav* for murder, right? Right. Right. The fact
that it's not born yet means that you would not be executed
in a court for killing it, but maybe it would be everything
but, okay? We don't know exactly what its middle status is. אמר
רב amar Rav, יהודה אמר שמואל *Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel*, האישה
היוצאה ליהרג *ha'isha hayotzei lehareg*, now if there was any if the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before maybe, you know, would have been ambiguous about
the issues about abortion, this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* certainly seems to certainly
weigh in on one side. Let's take a look. האישה היוצאה ליהרג
*ha'isha hayotzei lehareg*, this woman's about to be executed, מכין אותה makin
osa, כנגד בית ההריון כדי שימות הולד תחילה *makkin osah keneged beis
haherayon kedei sheyamus havalad techilah*. You don't just execute her and then
the child dies naturally. You actually first abort the fetus and then
you kill her. Why should you do such a thing? כדי שלא
תבוא לידי ניוול nivul, *kedei shelo tavo lidei nivul*. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* thinks that if you execute the woman and the fetus is
not yet born and then the fetus will be thrashing around inside
and eventually, you know, and then die, that will be, you know,
that will be a not what's the word ניוול *nivul*, not disgusting,
degradation, you mean degradation, not humiliation, she's dead, but whatever. Anyway, anyway,
somehow it would be degrading or degradation, anyway, to the corpse because
the dead corpse and now this fetus is thrashing around and then
it's dying, so it's not respectful to the woman's corpse and her
body. And therefore, because we're concerned about that, we're going to abort
the fetus. So now it's particularly powerful. It's not saying we execute
the woman and the fetus dies naturally, which you could then say
is not really making a comment about abortion, it's making a comment
about executing the mother. Here we actually directly abort the fetus for
the purpose of this. Why not do a cesarean and have the
baby? I think it's assuming that, I think it's assuming that, well,
here's the interesting question. Is it assuming that the child is nine
months pregnant, you know, assuming? Right, right. So it could be that
the child is, it could right, it could be that the child
is inviable. But remember the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* only draws the line
of the moment of childbirth. So presumably we're talking nine full months,
she could give birth any minute, but she hasn't begun yet, and
even if the child is viable, and presumably is the case, and
presumably the answer is, is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said of
מענין דינו *me'annin dino*. You don't want to postpone her execution even
for one minute. So what if the father wants the child? The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says we don't care, the פסוק *pasuk* tells us
we reject the father's claim. But again, the fact that, I mean,
it's a good point that we're talking even in the case where
she's nine full months pregnant and you could maybe wait an hour
and have her give birth or do a cesarean section and do
it even in less time, and we don't do it for the
sake of execution because we're executing her, you know, I think that
makes a, okay, it seems a little cruel, I mean, very cruel
in terms of a life that's wasted and the father, right, right,
and to be... I understand, I understand, and all of this is
in the name of מענין דינו *me'annin dino*. So it really makes
a statement, I think, about, you know, about how much this is
considered the taking of a life or not in terms of, but
even if it were, and this is the other problem the שיטה
מקובצת *Shita Mekubetzes* raises and the רמב"ן Ramban *Ramban* raises and it's
the flip side of the problem and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going
to get to a little bit, is we would be מחלל שבת
mechallel Shabbat. *mechallel Shabbos* if a fetus was at risk, right? And
so if this is enough of a potential life... That you're מחלל
שבת mechallel Shabbat to save it, how could it not factor significantly
enough that you should therefore wait to have it give birth in
order to, if it certainly maybe if you have to wait three
months you could say no that goes against but to wait an
hour, half hour, and that's really a very powerful question. I mean,
put the abortion question aside. How could we not be so sort
of callous about this potential about this almost almost full life? And
that's a question that the ראשונים Rishonim raise. And it's a very
good question. What's the answer? They really don't have a good answer.
No, I I really don't see this from the woman's perspective. They're
looking they seem to be looking at it to be kinder to
the mother. Right. But once she's dead, she's not going to be
embarrassed. At this point to beat her and cause her to deliver
right there with people watching is going to be worse. I totally
agree. I have yeah. The way the גמרא Gemara? describes it, מכין
makin. אותה, it's like we can't wait so as we're walking to
you know to you know to the cliff we hit her and
whatever. Right. Yeah. It's just despair. Right. Yeah. I know. I I
can I know. I can't I can't explain it. You're right. I
totally agree. And you'd think you could do such a thing in
you know with an injection or something and you know. Right. But
that's not what they say. They didn't have injections back then. Okay.
True. They say מכין. Right. All right. Let's all right. It is
it is a very challenging גמרא. Gemara. Let's get a little further.
My goal is to finish the פרק perek today. Okay, not the
דף, daf, but at least the פרק. perek. Let's keep on going.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara, says, למימרא, lememra, so the only
sort of thing the גמרא Gemara. focuses in on is the following.
למימרא דהיא קדמה מיתה, lememra de-hi kadma misa, so your whole concern
indicates that you think that if we execute her, she'll die first
and the fetus later and that will lead to the ניוול, the
degradation. והא קיימא לן דולד מיית ברישא, ve-ha kaima lan de-vlad mayis
breisha, we have a principle that we believe that when a mother
dies with a fetus, that the fetus dies first and then the
mother. דתנן, de-snan, and how do you know it? Because the משנה
Mishnah. says, תינוק בן יומו נוחל ומנחיל, tinok ben yomo nochel u-manchil,
that a infant even one day old can inherit and bequeath. So
basically a child is born, his mother dies in childbirth let's say,
he inherits from his mother, then he dies, and then his inheritance
that he got from his mother passes on to his brothers and
so on. Okay, so that's once he's already born. Okay, so ואמר
רב ששת, ve-amar Rav Sheshes, נוחל בנכסי האם להנחיל לאחין מן האב,
nochel be-nichsei ha-eim le-hanchil le-achin min ha-av, inherits from the mother and
then passes on to his brothers even if they're from a different
mother because if somebody dies, his brothers from the same father are
his heirs if he has no son. Okay, so that's why it
matters that he inherited and passed on because it goes from the
mother to the son and then to his brothers from a different
mother. Anyway, that's the case. דוקא בן יום אחד, davka ben yom
echad, it's only if he's already born. אבל עובר לא, aval ubar
lo, but if he was a fetus, not. Now of course you
would say why not if he's a fetus? Because he's not yet
a legal entity. Right? But the גמרא Gemara, understands that the reason
not by a fetus is forget the question of whether he's a
legal entity, the order won't work. Because he'll die and then the
mother will die, so therefore it will be irrelevant anyway. דהוא מיית
ברישא, de-hu mayis breisha, because he'll always die first. ואין הבן יורש
את אמו בקבר, ve-ein ha-ben yoresh es imo ba-kever, and a son
can't inherit from his mother in the grave. Once he's already dead,
he cannot be the heir of his mother once he's already dead.
להנחיל לאחין מן האב, le-hanchil le-achin min ha-av, and then to pass
on to his brothers. So if the son is dead and the
mother dies and the mother has no children, it'll pass on to
the mother's family, her you know her father, her brothers and so
on. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara explains it not because he's
not yet a legal entity, but because he will die first. Maybe
the גמרא Gemara understands that here that if the mother died first
and he was full term, then even though he hadn't been born
and even though he was in the womb, now it's like he
is born now that the mother is dead, now he's just like
you know now he just has some dead skin around him. Anyway,
it's an interesting why the גמרא Gemara does not suggest that it's
because he's not an entity, rather says because he dies first. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says, you see, we think that when the mother
dies, the infant dies first. So why do you assume that it's
the opposite? So the גמרא says, הני מילי לגבי מיתה, hani mili
legabi misa, that's about natural death. איידי דולד זוטרא חיותיה, aidi de-vlad
zutra chayusei, because the infant has very little life, right, it's very
tenuous of a hold on life. עייל טיפה דמלאך המות, ayal tipa
de-malach ha-maves, so the drop from the angel of death, one assumes
that this is metaphorical, goes in. ומחתך להו לסימנין, u-mechatech lehu le-simanin,
and kills the infant's like סימנים simanim as we know means the
trachea and esophagus first. Basically what it means is in the process
of natural death, so therefore because the fetus's life is more tenuous
and and therefore we assume that he that the process of dying
that will have an impact on the fetus first because it's a
slow gradual process and whatever you know is causing the death will
somehow lead to the fetus to die. אבל נהרג, aval neherag, but
if it is a violent death, she's been executed. היא מתה ברישא,
hi mesa breisha, then it's instantaneous, it's violent, and there's no you
know it's not like the cancer gets to the baby. So therefore
we'll assume that it's possible that she will die first and therefore
we're concerned about the ניוול המת
nivul ha-meis if she dies first and the fetus is still alive.
So Gemara says והוי עובדא ופרכס תלת פרכוסי. v'havai uvda uparchis tlas
pirchusei. How can you say that the child dies first by a
natural death? We know there are cases of natural death and the
fetus was
thrashing around after the mother died. So the Gemara says, yeah, מידי
דהוה אדנבא דלטאה. midi d'hava adnava d'lata'a. That's like the, that's like
the tail of a lizard. You cut off the tail of a
lizard and it still thrashes around. So that doesn't indicate real life,
that's just that still some spontaneous motion. Okay, so the Gemara is
very insistent on its belief that it always is the same, that
when it's a natural death, the mother dies first, excuse me, the
mother dies first, no, when it's a natural
death, the fetus dies first and then the mother. Even though it's
trying to insist that this always happens, now we're going to sort
of
see a case opposite that. דמפרכסת, d'mifarkeset, that thrashes around. אמר רב
נחמן אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, האישה שישבה על המשבר,
ha'isha sheyashva al hamashber, a woman is sitting in childbirth, ומתה בשבת,
umeta b'Shabbat, and she died on Shabbat. Now here, מביאין סכין ומקרעין
את כריסה, mevi'in sakin umekarin et kreisa, you can bring a knife
and, you know, do a cesarean section, ומוציאין את הולד, umotzi'in et
havlad, and take out the child. Now before we get any further
to discuss this, I don't understand. Didn't we just say that the
fetus dies first? You know, so I would have said dying in
childbirth is more like a violent death than a natural death, but
you know, because it's more, it's you know, it's not like a
slow sickness. But Rashi says, you know, look at the last Rashi,
דזימנין דמקדמי אימיה ומיתה. d'zimnin d'mikadmi imei umita.
No, sometimes actually she does die first. So if we're ready to
admit that sometimes she does
die first, why did we have to go through all of the
rigmarole before? So I don't know exactly. You certainly look at the
dying in childbirth as a separate category. That's what I just said,
similar to the violent case. But Rashi doesn't. So if Rashi says,
you know, sometimes it does happen this way, so then why didn't
the, why was the Gemara so insistent that it could never happen?
Anyway, for whatever reason, so bracketing whether who dies first, in this
scenario we would do a cesarean section to save the child. פשיטא,
Pshita, of course. Now why is it of course? מאי עביד? Mai
avid? Because you're not even doing a מלאכה. melacha. If you cut
into dead, if the mother is dead, if you cut into a
live person or animal, that's חבלה. chavala. But if you cut into
a dead animal, well, that's what you do when you have meat
on Shabbat, you cut into it and blood comes out, that's not
חבלה. chavala. So if you cut into the mother's womb after she's
dead, it's not a מלאכה melacha on Shabbat. So there's not, I
mean, this is, you know, it's of course obvious. חתיכת בשר הוא,
Chatichat basar hu, just cutting into meat. I know, but when there's,
there's no חידוש, chiddush, not, yes, but there's no חידוש, chiddush, oh,
you can be מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbat. There's no מחלל שבת mechallel
Shabbat. to save the fetus. You're not even being מחלל שבת. mechallel
Shabbat, There's a question, if you're not even telling us such a
big חידוש? chiddush? So the Gemara says, אמר רבא לא נצרכה אלא
להביא סכין דרך רשות הרבים. Amar Rava lo nitzrecha ela l'havi sakin
derech reshut harabim. No, you could be מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbat Let's
say you have to go bring the knife across רשות הרבים. reshut
harabim. So don't bother me with the details, in a case where
you have to be מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbat. you can be מחלל
שבת mechallel Shabbat to save the life of a fetus. ומה קמשמע
לן? U'mai kamashma lan? Right. ומה קמשמע לן, U'mai kamashma lan, what
does this tell us? דמידי ספיקא מחללינן שבתא, d'midi sefeika mechalelinan Shabta,
that because of a ספק, safek, why is it ספק? safek? Because
the fetus might die, right? It's, you know, who knows if it's
going to be a successful delivery. Nevertheless, you're allowed to be מחלל
שבת. mechallel Shabbat That's not a חידוש. chiddush. תנינא, Tanina, we taught
it. מי שנפלה עליו מפולת, Mi shenafela alav mapolet, if somebody had
a building fall on him, ספק הוא שם ספק אינו שם, safek
hu sham safek eino sham, you don't even know if the person
was in the building when it collapsed. ספק חי ספק מת, Safek
chai safek met, you don't even know if he's still alive or
maybe he's dead. ספק כנעני, Safek Kna'ani, which is an edited text
because really it's just גוי. goy. ספק ישראל, Safek Yisrael, you don't
know Jewish or not Jewish, which gets to the whole question about
being מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat for a non-Jew, which we're going to
bracket now, we'll discuss when we get to יומא. Yoma. I'm not,
they'll discuss when we get to יומא. Yoma. Anyway, מפקחין עליו את
הגל. mefakchin alav et hagal. You can be מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat,
even if it's, you don't, even though there's so many doubts, you
can be מחלל שבת mechalel Shabbos because you might save a life.
So what's the חידוש chiddush here? So the Gemara says, no, מהו
דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought, התם הוא דאית ליה חזקה
דחיותא. hatam hu d'it lei chazaka d'chiyuta. There the person had already
established a status of being alive. He was a living, breathing person.
אבל הכא דלא אית ליה חזקה דחיותא, aval hacha d'lo it lei
chazaka d'chiyuta, here he hasn't established it, the fetus, מעיקרא, me'ikara, originally,
אימא לא, eima lo, maybe we wouldn't be מחלל שבת, mechalel Shabbos
קמשמע לן kamashma lan that you do. Now, what does it mean
that he hasn't established? Why is that significant? You could frame that
in two ways. One way you could frame it is means, means
that if, well, one it has to do with the status of
the fetus, the other has to do with the viability. One way
to frame it is about the question of viability. Somebody is already
viable, then if there's introduced doubts, maybe he's no longer alive, but
we knew he was, we knew he was living and breathing and
therefore we'll assume he's still living and breathing and we'll work on
that assumption and we'll try to preserve his living and breathing status.
אם תמצי לומר, Im timtzi lomar, right, ממה נפשך. mima nafshach. If,
however, he was never living and breathing, he's, so there's a question
like viability, we can't assume he's still living and breathing, we can't
assume we'll be successful, we won't do it. So one way to
frame it, להבא אמינא, l'hava amina, and then we reject it, we
save the fetus. But one way to frame it is that it's
a question of viability. The other way to frame it though is
this question about status, that this guy was already a person. The
fetus is not, חזקה דחיותא chazaka d'chiyuta might mean, although it sounds
more like it's viability, he's not... that yet a halakhic person. He
had to have been born. Maybe I wouldn't be מחלל שבת mechalel
Shabbos for somebody who's not yet a halakhic person. קא משמע לן
kamashmalan that they are now. How much, how far are you מחלל
שבת mechalel Shabbos. for a fetus? So here it says the woman
was ישבה על המשבר, which remember in our משנה Mishnah, already gave
the fetus independent status. Would you be מחלל שבת mechalel Shabbos, for
a fetus three months old? Would you know, if she's three months
pregnant? So, you know, the ראשונים, Rishonim, you know, basically totally assume
yes, although there are some that basically say it's the flip side
of the abortion debate. You can't have it both ways. If you
can have an abortion, then you can't be מחלל שבת. mechalel Shabbos
But actually there are those that definitely split the פסק, psak, and
how you can split
the פסק psak is an interesting question. Anyway, the most fascinating question
is can you be מחלל שבת,
mechalel Shabbos the רמב"ן Ramban raises this in תורת האדם, Toras HaAdam,
for a fetus less than 40 days old? Because less than 40
days, it's almost universal that the threshold to abort at that stage
is like very, very low. And even so, if she's pregnant, even
so the רמב"ן says, and I think it meant... but anyway the
הלכה halacha basically is that yes, you can be מחלל שבת mechalel
Shabbos if a woman is less than 40 days pregnant and there's
a question about the viability, you can even be מחלל שבת because
of the potential life. So the question becomes how can you have
it both ways? Have a very broad allowance if you want to
save the life to מחלל שבת and also try to argue for
a broad allowance if you want to abort? That is a very
interesting question which we are not going to answer. Okay, now let's
get to in the next five minutes, let's get to the משנה.
Which is the pro-abortion people use. They call themselves pro-choice. In הלכה,
halacha, pro-choice. Yeah, you're right. Pro-choice. Yes. Do they use this גמרא?
Of course. So they do use this גמרא. It can go either
way though. This גמרא, pre-Rav Moshe, there was always the general consensus
was that there's a question about what threshold you needed to abort,
but certainly nobody was putting it in the category of like a
type of quasi-רציחה. retzichah. Rav Moshe came out with the position that
it's almost like רציחה retzichah and it completely sort of changed the
tenor of the debate. You can, I'll just say one last thing
about this. You can sometimes, sometimes you can see where a תשובה
teshuvah is going by the first sentence. Here's a case where you
know where the תשובה teshuvah is going by the title of it.
If you look at the title of the ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer
about abortion, who's very liberal, the title of his תשובה teshuvah is
בעניין הפלת עוברים, be'inyan hapalas ubarim, relating to the aborting of fetuses.
Okay, if you look at the title of Rav Moshe, בעניין רציחת
עוברים, be'inyan retzichas ubarim, about the murder of fetuses. Right. Okay, let's
keep, let's finish up the גמרא. ואימא סיפא, ve'eima seifa, ומר סבר,
umar savar, האישה שנהרגה, ha'ishah shenehergah, hair is not איסורי הנאה. issurei
hana'ah. ואמאי, ve'amai, says the גמרא, איסורי הנאה נינהו, issurei hana'ah ninhu,
it should be איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, it's part of her body.
אמר רב, amar Rav, באומרת תנו שיערי לבתי. be'omeres tenu se'ari leviti.
She says, oh, I want, she indicates that she's not considering her
hair part of her body. She bequeaths it to her daughter to
make a nice wig out of it. Okay, so the גמרא says
who cares? אילו אמר תנו ידי לבתי, ilu amar tenu yadi leviti,
מי יהבינן לה? mi yahavinan lah? So she can't determine what's part
of her body. If she said give my hand, we wouldn't say
it's not part of her body. So אמר רב, בפאה נוכרית. bepe'ah
nochris. We're talking about a wig. Now, so what's the חידוש chiddush
about the wig? The חידוש chiddush is as we're going to see,
it's I don't know, they call it not a fall, but some
type of a thing where they would sort of weave hair into
her hair. So it actually was woven in and connected. So I
might have thought that now because it's woven in, it's defined as
part of her body. And we're saying no, since ultimately it is
not her natural hair, it is not. Only if she says give
it to my daughter. So okay, we're going to talk about that.
טעמא דאמר תנו, ta'ama de'amar tenu, so you're saying in the case
of the woven-in hair, it's only because she says give it to
my daughter and that makes it separate. הא לא אמר תנו, ha
lo amar tenu, גופא הוא, gufa hu, ומיתסר, umis'ar, you would consider
it her body and you say it's forbidden. Is that really true?
והא מיבעיא ליה לרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, veha miba'ya lei le-Rabbi Yossi
b'Rabbi Chanina, this was a question Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Chanina raised. בעי
רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, ba'ei Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Chanina, שיער נשים צדקניות,
se'ar nashim tzidkaniyos, מהו? mahu? The hair of the righteous women. Do
you think like we're reading now about שמות, Shemos, בזכות נשים צדקניות
נגאלו אבותינו, bizchus nashim tzidkaniyos nigalu avoseinu, that's not what it means.
נשים צדקניות nashim tzidkaniyos is by עיר הנדחת. ir hanidachas. In עיר
הנדחת, ir hanidachas, basically the men and women who did not sin
do not get killed. But because it says כל שללה, kol shelalah,
all of the property, basically they have to leave the עיר הנדחת
ir hanidachas naked. They leave behind all of their property, they get
saved, right, and they leave behind all their property to get destroyed.
So the question is, you have a woman who's leaving and she
has to leave behind all of her property, what about her hair,
this hair that's woven in? Is that her body or is that
her property? Okay, so that was the question raised. שיער נשים צדקניות,
se'ar nashim tzidkaniyos, the hair, now again we're assuming this means the
hair that's woven in, מהו? mahu? But again, he just said hair.
We've now qualified it, ואמר רבא בפאה נוכרית קמיבעיא ליה. ve'amar Rava
bepe'ah nochris kamiba'ya lei. The question is not hair, again, simple sense
of the משנה, simple sense of this is that the hair's not
part of the body. The גמרא takes it for granted that it
is and shifts the discussion to the woven-in hair, to the wig.
So Rava says we're talking about the wig. So you see there,
he doesn't know whether to consider it part of the body and
you would say that unless she said תנו, tenu, it's definitely part
of the body, how do you resolve that? The גמרא says כי
קא מיבעיא ליה לרב יצחק בר חנינא, ki ka miba'aya lei leRav
Yitzchak bar Chanina, why did he have a doubt? דתלי בסכס. detali
besichas. That really was not so much woven in. That was like
hanging by a peg. Meaning that was sort of like a wig.
Okay, so a wig that she wore, there he was saying maybe
it's considered since she always wears it, maybe it's like her body,
maybe it's like her property. That's the only doubt. That's where he
didn't know. הכא, hacha, here where we by default treat it like
part of her body, דמחבר בה, demchaber bah, that it's woven in.
טעמא דאמר תנו ta'ama de'amar tenu and only therefore only if she
says give it, הא לא אמר תנו halo lo amar tenu if
she doesn't say it, גופה הוא gufah hu it's part of her
body. So now we have basically said we're only at most talking
about woven-in hair, but the hair itself is part of her body.
But we're not done. So let's take a look. This really shouldn't
be a תיובתא. tiyuvta. קשיא ליה לרב נחמן בר יצחק. kashya lei
leRav Nachman bar Yitzchak. So now רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak was bothered with this whole discussion. דדומיא דבהמה קתני, dedumya
debehema katani, it says like the animal. מה התם ma hasam an
animals don't wear wigs or woven-in hair. So מה התם גופא, ma
hasam gufa, the same way there we're talking about the body itself
being forbidden and you know we're saying by the animal it's forbidden,
by the woman we say it's permissible, הכא נמי גופה hacha nami
gufah here too we're talking about her real hair. Okay, so because
it's by the same way saying by the animal fully forbidden, the
woman her hair's okay, presumably we mean her real hair. אלא אמר
רב נחמן, ella amar Rav Nachman, her real hair is permitted. Why?
זו מיתתה אוסרתה zu misasah osartah oh sorry, וזו גמר דינה אוסרתה.
vezu gmar dinah osartah. When an animal is defined to be executed,
is going to be executed because of the day it gored, we
say that it is forbidden in הנאה hana'ah before it's executed. Once
it is ruled that it has to be stoned, it's already forbidden
in הנאה. hana'ah. So once the בית דין beis din said it's
going to be stoned, the whole animal was deemed as forbidden and
it includes the wool of the hair and whatever. But let's say
a woman is going to be executed. She's not forbidden in הנאה
hana'ah before she's executed. She can, I don't know, nurse her child,
she... there's no איסור הנאה issur hana'ah on a human. You know,
she... the... the execution, the writ of execution doesn't make her forbidden.
Why is she forbidden? She's forbidden like any other human being who
dies, that their body is forbidden, not because she was executed. Okay,
so why does that not apply to the hair? So the גמרא
doesn't spell it out, but רש"י basically says because the hair doesn't
die. The person's death... well, he doesn't say that, but that's of
course the first thing I thought. You know, hair actually continues to
grow on a corpse, I think up to like a month after
death. Is that right, Charlie? You're... you're... anyway, anyway, anyway, but certainly
the experience of death is on, you know, the sort of the
living organism and the hair is basically dead. You know, the hair
is dead. I mean, new hair grows, but the hair is already
dead. So the death doesn't occur to hair, and therefore actually this
is a general הלכה halacha that even though a dead body is
אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, it does not apply to the hair because
although hair is part of the body, it's not considered to have
died. Okay, so let's just finish this up. No, I said because
it grows. רש"י, I think רש"י would say because it's already dead.
It's dead, it's dead, you know, it's dead skin. So therefore it
does not die and therefore it's not forbidden. Let's just finish this
up. תני רמי כוותיה דרב, tani Rami kevasei deRav, תני רמי כוותיה
דרב נחמן בר יצחק. tani Rami kevasei deRav Nachman bar Yitzchak. We
have support for both approaches. תני רמי כוותיה דרב, tani Rami kevasei
deRav, האשה שיצאה ליהרג ואמרה תנו שערי לבתי ונותנין, ha'ishah sheyatzah lehareig
ve'amrah tenu se'ari leviti venosnin, מתה אין נותנין. meisah ein nosnin. If
so if she says, if she dies, you don't give it. מפני
שהמת אסור בהנאה. mipnei shemeis assur behana'ah. Because a מת meis is
forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. Why you have to spell that out? We
know that to be an issue. פשיטא. peshita. אלא, ella, what it
means is שנויי המת אסור בהנאה. shenoyei hameis assur behana'ah. Even though
it's only an adornment, even though it's only woven in, nevertheless it's
forbidden unless she says give the, give it to my daughter. So
that shows you only if she says give it to my daughter
and only the way we're reading it if it's woven-in hair. תני
כוותיה דרב נחמן בר יצחק, tani kevasei deRav Nachman bar Yitzchak, and
we talk about the other approach which is it's totally permissible. האשה
שמתה נהנין בשערה ha'ishah shemeisah nehenin bise'arah straight away. A woman dies,
hair is okay. בהמה שנהרגה אסור בהנאה. behema she'nehergah assur behana'ah. ומה
הפרש בין זה לזה? umah hefresh bein zeh lezeh? Why is the
hair of a woman different than let's say the wool of a
sheep? זו מיתתה אוסרתה zu misasah osartah וזו גמר דינה אוסרתה. vezu
gmar dinah osartah. One it's the death and for some reason the
death, like we said, does not apply to hair, the other it's
the ruling of the בית דין beis din and that applies to
the entire animal. הדרן עלך כל המאורס. hadran alach kol hame'arus. Oh
my god, what a דף. daf.